We said that there are two types of
snooping coherence approaches. One was
write update. The other is write
invalidate. So going back to our
optimize write update setup where we had
the valid and the tag bits also the
dirty bit for write back caches and a
shared bit that tells us whether we are
alone in this. A write invalidate
protocol will broadcast rights on the
bus so that they can be seen by
everybody. But instead of updating their
copies, they will invalidate them. So
let's see how this works. Let's say this
score reads
a. We send this get the value from
memory. Now we have it as valid, not
dirty. The tag is a the value is let's
say zero and it's not shared. Let's say
now we have the right to a and write one
to it. We have a cache miss. We
broadcast the right. We now don't need
to broadcast the value with it because
the other caches don't need this value.
What's going to happen is as we send
this to the bus, it's going to be
snooped by this cache and it sees that
somebody is trying to write to the block
that I have in my cache. In a right
update protocol, we would now need the
value to put it here. In a right
invalidate protocol, all we do is change
the valid bit to zero. So now we will
miss in the cache next time we read this
particular cache now gets the valid it's
not shared every time we do a write and
broadcast it we know it's not shared
because all the other copies have been
destroyed so a write makes the block
non-shared in the writing processor it
is dirty and now it has a value of one
so now a read of a here in a right
update protocol would be a hit and just
read here but in a right invalid date
protocol, the read will still get the
new value. It's not going to be
incoherent because it doesn't get the
value of zero. It will now be a miss and
be sent to the bus. Now, the memory has
not been updated yet, but the processor
who has the dirty data and matches the
address of the block will see that there
is a read request on the bus and respond
with the data. So now the block becomes
valid. Somebody gave us the data. So
definitely now it's shared. we get the
data and the cache where we wrote now
also knows it's shared because we gave
it to somebody. So clearly we are not
the only one who has it anymore. So now
note that just like in a right update
protocol if we have a lot of reads now
they can have cash hits another write
will invalidate this. So there will be a
cache miss also. So the disadvantage of
write invalidate protocols is that there
is a miss on all the readers when
somebody writes. However, there is an
advantage to it as well in that if you
need to update the same block twice.
Let's say you write two to a, we
invalidate this copy by broadcasting.
Now the block is no longer shared. We
put two there. So we had a broadcast for
this first write. If we now do some more
reads and writes, they can all be done
locally. We don't have to broadcast
them. So basically by invalidating this
copy we made ourselves be the only one
who has the block and now we don't need
to broadcast all the rights. So for
anything where one core works on it for
a while then another one works on it for
a while. If the work involves writing
only the first write really has to be
broadcast after that it's a local access
for both reads and writes. In contrast
with write update we would have to keep
updating the other cache until it
replaces the block. Just like with write
update, write invalidate can benefit
from the same type of optimization when
we are writing two different blocks and
accessing it later. So in that case B is
fetched here is not shared becomes dirty
and C is fetched here is not shared
becomes dirty and gets a value of one.
And now we can have cache hits on both
reads and writes without going to the
bus for B here. And we can access C here
with no going to the bus. So for blocks
that are only accessed on one core, we
have the same behavior for both write
update and write
invalidate. But for blocks that are
shared, we get different behavior. Write
update tends to result in more hits but
does more broadcasts if we repeatedly
update. Write invalidate generates a
miss on all the readers after a right
occurred but it allows us to locally
write after the first write. Note that
with write update we ensured for a that
the second property of coherence is
maintained by updating all the copies.
So when a right occurs all copies are up
to date and thus they will return the
new value of the right. With write
invalidate we ensure the same property
by the right invalidating all the other
copies. So that now they have no choice
but to get the new version of the data.
So either way reads will get the new
version of the data but that is achieved
in different ways. The third property of
coherence is still ensured by snooping
in a right invalidate protocol with
snooping. So basically snooping on the
bus still ensures that any rights that
need to go to the bus because there is
sharing will be ordered by the order to
which they go to the bus. So for example
a right here will invalidate everything.
Now a right here has to put a request on
the bus because it's a miss and thus
obtain the copy from here and now
everybody knows what the order was. In
fact, at any given time, only the last
version really survives in caches
because a right invalidates all the
other copies. So, it's pretty clear
whose version was last because all the
readers need to get the copy that was
written last anyway.